Mark Zuckerberg,
مارك زوكربيرج،
a journalist was asking him a question about the news feed.
أحد الصحافيين كان يسأله حول التغذية الإخبارية.
And the journalist was asking him,
والصحفي كان يسأله،
"Why is this so important?"
"لماذا هذا في غاية الأهمية؟"
And Zuckerberg said,
فقال زوكربيرج،
"A squirrel dying in your front yard
"سنجاب يموت في فنائكم
may be more relevant to your interests right now
قد يكون ذا صلة أكبر باهتماماتك الآن
than people dying in Africa."
من الناس الذين يموتون في أفريقيا."
And I want to talk about
وأريد التحدث عن
what a Web based on that idea of relevance might look like.
ما الذي قد تبدو عليه شبكة انترنت تعتمد فكرة الصلة.
So when I was growing up
هكذا حين نشأت
in a really rural area in Maine,
في منطقة قروية في مين،
the Internet meant something very different to me.
كان الانترنت يعني شيئا مختلفا بالنسبة لي.
It meant a connection to the world.
كان يعني اتصالا بالعالم.
It meant something that would connect us all together.
كان يعني شيئا سوف يصلنا جميعا ببعضنا البعض.
And I was sure that it was going to be great for democracy
وكنت متأكدا بأنه سيكون أمرا عظيما للديموقراطية
and for our society.
ولمجتمعنا.
But there's this shift
لكن حصلت هذه النقلة
in how information is flowing online,
في كيفية تدفق المعلومات على الانترنت،
and it's invisible.
وهي غير مرئية.
And if we don't pay attention to it,
وإن لم نعرها اهتماما،
it could be a real problem.
قد تكون مشكلا حقيقيا.
So I first noticed this in a place I spend a lot of time --
وبالتالي لاحظت هذا في مكان أقضي فيه الكثير من الوقت --
my Facebook page.
صفحتي على الفيسبوك.
I'm progressive, politically -- big surprise --
أنا تقدمي، سياسيا -- مفاجأة كبيرة --
but I've always gone out of my way to meet conservatives.
لكنني دائما ما ذهبت بعيدا عن طريقي للقاء المحافظين.
I like hearing what they're thinking about;
يعجبني سماع ما يفكرون فيه؛
I like seeing what they link to;
يعجبني رؤية ما يربطون إليه؛
I like learning a thing or two.
يعجبني تعلم أمر أو اثنين.
And so I was surprised when I noticed one day
وهكذا تفاجأت حين لاحظت في أحد الأيام
that the conservatives had disappeared from my Facebook feed.
أن المحافظين قد اختفوا من تغذيتي الإخبارية على الفيسبوك.
And what it turned out was going on
والذي اتضح أنه يحصل
was that Facebook was looking at which links I clicked on,
هو أن فيسبوك كان ينظر إلى أي الروابط أنقر عليها،
and it was noticing that, actually,
وكان يلاحظ ذلك، في الواقع،
I was clicking more on my liberal friends' links
كنت أنقر أكثر على روابط أصدقائي الليبراليين
than on my conservative friends' links.
من روابط أصدقائي المحافظين.
And without consulting me about it,
وبدون أن يستشيرني بخصوص الأمر،
it had edited them out.
قام بتحريرهم وإبعادهم.
They disappeared.
اختفت.
So Facebook isn't the only place
لذا فيسبوك ليس المكان الوحيد
that's doing this kind of invisible, algorithmic
الذي يقوم بهذا النوع الخفي، اللوغاريثمي
editing of the Web.
من تحرير الانترنت.
Google's doing it too.
غوغل تقوم بذلك ايضا.
If I search for something, and you search for something,
إن بحثت عن شيء ما، وبحثتَ عنه،
even right now at the very same time,
وحتى في نفس اللحظة الآن،
we may get very different search results.
قد نحصل على نتائج بحث مختلفة للغاية.
Even if you're logged out, one engineer told me,
حتى إن كنت سجلت الخروج من حسابك، أحد المهندسين أخبرني،
there are 57 signals
هناك 57 إشارة
that Google looks at --
تنظر إليها غوغل --
everything from what kind of computer you're on
كل شيء بدء من نوع الكمبيوتر الذي تستخدمه
to what kind of browser you're using
إلى نوع المتصفح الذي تستعمله
to where you're located --
إلى المكان الذي توجد فيه --
that it uses to personally tailor your query results.
والتي تستخدمها لتصميم نتائج بحث شخصية.
Think about it for a second:
فكروا في الأمر لثانية:
there is no standard Google anymore.
لم يعد هناك وجود لغوغل قياسي.
And you know, the funny thing about this is that it's hard to see.
وتعرفون، المضحك في الأمر هو أنه من الصعب رؤيته.
You can't see how different your search results are
لا تستطيع رؤية مدى اختلاف نتائج بحثك
from anyone else's.
عن أي شخص آخر.
But a couple of weeks ago,
لكن قبل بضعة أسابيع،
I asked a bunch of friends to Google "Egypt"
طلبت من مجموعة من الأصدقاء أن يبحثوا في غوغل عن "مصر"
and to send me screen shots of what they got.
وأن يرسلوا لي لقطات لما حصلوا عليه.
So here's my friend Scott's screen shot.
وبالتالي ها هي لقطة صديقي سكوت.
And here's my friend Daniel's screen shot.
وها هي لقطة صديقي دانييل.
When you put them side-by-side,
حين تضعونهما جنبا إلى جنب،
you don't even have to read the links
لا تحتاج حتى إلى قراءة الروابط
to see how different these two pages are.
لرؤية امدى اختلاف الصفحتين.
But when you do read the links,
لكن حين تقرؤون الروابط،
it's really quite remarkable.
إنه أمر لافت حقا.
Daniel didn't get anything about the protests in Egypt at all
لم يحصل دانييل على أي شيء حول التظاهرات في مصر على الإطلاق
in his first page of Google results.
في صفحته الأولى من نتائج بحث غوغل.
Scott's results were full of them.
نتائج بحث سكوت كانت مليئة بها.
And this was the big story of the day at that time.
وتلك كانت القصة الكبيرة آنذاك.
That's how different these results are becoming.
هذا مدى الاختلاف الذي وصلت إليه نتائج البحث.
So it's not just Google and Facebook either.
إذن فليس فقط غوغل أو حتى فيسبوك.
This is something that's sweeping the Web.
هذا أمر يغطي شبكة الانترنت.
There are a whole host of companies that are doing this kind of personalization.
هناك عدد كبير من الشركات تقوم بنفس النوع من التخصيص.
Yahoo News, the biggest news site on the Internet,
أخبار ياهوو، أكبر موقع إخباري على الانترنت،
is now personalized -- different people get different things.
هو الآن مخصص -- أشخاص مختلفون يحصلون على أشياء مختلفة.
Huffington Post, the Washington Post, the New York Times --
هافينغتون بوست، الواشنطون بوست، النيويورك تايمز --
all flirting with personalization in various ways.
كلهم يتغازلون بالتخصيص بطرق مختلفة.
And this moves us very quickly
وهذا ينقلنا بشكل سريع
toward a world in which
إلى عالم حيث
the Internet is showing us what it thinks we want to see,
يظهر لنا الانترنت ما يعتقد أننا نريد رؤيته،
but not necessarily what we need to see.
لكن ليس بالضرورة ما نريد رؤيته.
As Eric Schmidt said,
كما قال إريك شميت،
"It will be very hard for people to watch or consume something
"سيصبح من الصعب على الناس مشاهدة أو استهلاك شيء
that has not in some sense
لم يتم بمعنى ما
been tailored for them."
تخصيصه لهم."
So I do think this is a problem.
لذلك لا أعتقد أن هذا مشكل.
And I think, if you take all of these filters together,
وأعتقد أنه إن أخذت كل هذه المرشحات معا،
you take all these algorithms,
وأخذت كل هذه الخوارزميات،
you get what I call a filter bubble.
تحصل على ما أسميه فقاعة الترشيح.
And your filter bubble is your own personal,
وفقاعتك المرشحة هي عالم المعلومات
unique universe of information
الفريد الخاص بك
that you live in online.
الذي تعيش فيه على الانترنت.
And what's in your filter bubble
والموجود في فقاعتك المرشحة
depends on who you are, and it depends on what you do.
يعتمد على من تكون، يعتمد على ما تقوم به.
But the thing is that you don't decide what gets in.
لكن الحاصل هو أنك لا تقرر ما الذي يدخله.
And more importantly,
والأكثر أهمية،
you don't actually see what gets edited out.
لا ترى في الواقع ما الذي يحرر فيبعد.
So one of the problems with the filter bubble
وبالتالي أحد مشاكل الفقاعة المرشحة
was discovered by some researchers at Netflix.
تم اكتشافه من طرف الباحثين في نت فليكس(Netflix).
And they were looking at the Netflix queues, and they noticed something kind of funny
وقد كانوا ينظرون إلى قوائم نت فليكس، ولاحظوا أمرا مضحكا نوعا ما
that a lot of us probably have noticed,
الكثير منا لاحظه،
which is there are some movies
هو أن هناك أفلام
that just sort of zip right up and out to our houses.
تندفع نوعا ما نحو الأعلى وخارجا إلى بيوتنا.
They enter the queue, they just zip right out.
تدخل القائمة، وتندفع للتو خارجا.
So "Iron Man" zips right out,
وهكذا "Iron Man" اندفع للتو خارجا،
and "Waiting for Superman"
و"Waiting for Superman"
can wait for a really long time.
يمكن أن ينتظر لوقت طويل جدا.
What they discovered
ما اكتشفوه
was that in our Netflix queues
هو أن في قوائم نت فليكس الخاصة بنا
there's this epic struggle going on
يجري صراع ملحمي
between our future aspirational selves
بين أنفسنا الطموحة المستقبلية
and our more impulsive present selves.
وأنفسنا المندفعة الراهنية.
You know we all want to be someone
تدرون أننا جميعا نريد أن نكون مميزين
who has watched "Rashomon,"
من منكم شاهد "Rashomon،"
but right now
لكن حاليا
we want to watch "Ace Ventura" for the fourth time.
نريد أن نشاهد "Ace Ventura" للمرة الرابعة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So the best editing gives us a bit of both.
وهكذا فإن أحسن تحرير يعطينا قليلا من الأمرين.
It gives us a little bit of Justin Bieber
يعطينا القليل من Justin Bieber
and a little bit of Afghanistan.
والقليل من أفغانستان.
It gives us some information vegetables;
يعطينا بعض المعلومات خضرا،
it gives us some information dessert.
ويعطينا بعض المعلومات فاكهة.
And the challenge with these kinds of algorithmic filters,
والتحدي في هذا النوع من المرشحات الخوارزمية،
these personalized filters,
هذه المرشحات المخصصة،
is that, because they're mainly looking
هو أنه، بسبب أنها تنظر أساسا
at what you click on first,
إلى ما تنقر عليها أولا،
it can throw off that balance.
يمكن أن تتخلى عن ذلك التوازن.
And instead of a balanced information diet,
وبدل حمية معلومات متوازنة،
you can end up surrounded
قد تصبح محاطا
by information junk food.
بوجبات دون قيمة غذائية من المعلومات.
What this suggests
ما يوحي به هذا
is actually that we may have the story about the Internet wrong.
هو أنه في الواقع قد نكون مخطئين بخصوص الانترنت.
In a broadcast society --
في مجتمع ناشر --
this is how the founding mythology goes --
هكذا تقول الميثولوجيا المؤسسة --
in a broadcast society,
في مجتمع ناشر،
there were these gatekeepers, the editors,
كان هناك حراس بوابات، المحررون،
and they controlled the flows of information.
يتحكمون في تدفق المعلومات.
And along came the Internet and it swept them out of the way,
وثم جاء الانترنت فأزاحهم عن الطريق،
and it allowed all of us to connect together,
وسمح لنا جميعا بالإرتباط معا،
and it was awesome.
وقد كان أمرا ممتازا.
But that's not actually what's happening right now.
لكن ذلك ليس ما يحصل الآن في الواقع.
What we're seeing is more of a passing of the torch
ما نراه هو بالأحرى تسليم المشعل
from human gatekeepers
من حراس البوابات البشريين
to algorithmic ones.
إلى اللوغاريثميين.
And the thing is that the algorithms
والحاصل هو أن اللوغاريثمات
don't yet have the kind of embedded ethics
لا تمتلك بعد نوع الأخلاقيات المدمجة
that the editors did.
التي امتلكها المحررون.
So if algorithms are going to curate the world for us,
وبالتالي إن كانت اللوغاريثمات ستتحكم في عالمنا،
if they're going to decide what we get to see and what we don't get to see,
إن كانت ستقوم بتقرير ما يمكن أن نراه وما لا يمكن أن نراه،
then we need to make sure
حينها يجب أن نتيقن من
that they're not just keyed to relevance.
أنها لا تخضع فقط للصلة.
We need to make sure that they also show us things
يجب أن نتيقن من أنها ترينا كذلك أشياء
that are uncomfortable or challenging or important --
غير مريحة أو متحدية أو مهمة --
this is what TED does --
هذا ما يقوم به TED --
other points of view.
وجهات نظر أخرى.
And the thing is, we've actually been here before
والواقع أننا قد كنا في الحقيقة في نفس الوضع من قبل
as a society.
كمجتمع.
In 1915, it's not like newspapers were sweating a lot
في 1915، ليس أن الجرائد كانت تولي اهتماما
about their civic responsibilities.
لمسؤولياتها المدنية.
Then people noticed
فلاحظ الناس
that they were doing something really important.
أنه كانوا يقومون بشيء في غاية الأهمية.
That, in fact, you couldn't have
أنه، في الواقع، لا يمكن أن تكون لديك
a functioning democracy
ديموقراطية تعمل
if citizens didn't get a good flow of information,
إن لم يحصل المواطنون على تدفق جيد من المعلومات.
that the newspapers were critical because they were acting as the filter,
أن الصحف كانت خطيرة، لأنها كانت تعمل كمرشح،
and then journalistic ethics developed.
فتطورت أخلاقيات الصحفيين.
It wasn't perfect,
لم يكن الأمر مثاليا،
but it got us through the last century.
لكنه أفادنا خلال القرن الماضي.
And so now,
وهكذا الآن،
we're kind of back in 1915 on the Web.
نحن نوعا ما في 1915 على الانترنت.
And we need the new gatekeepers
ونرد من حراس البوابات الجدد
to encode that kind of responsibility
أن يرمزوا ذلك النوع من المسؤولية
into the code that they're writing.
في الترميز الذي يكتبونه.
I know that there are a lot of people here from Facebook and from Google --
أعلم أن هناك الكثير من الناس من فيسبوك وغوغل هنا --
Larry and Sergey --
لاري وسيرجي --
people who have helped build the Web as it is,
أشخاص ساعدوا في بناء شبكة الانترنت كما هي عليه،
and I'm grateful for that.
وأنا ممتن لذلك.
But we really need you to make sure
لكننا نحتاج حقا إلى التيقن
that these algorithms have encoded in them
من أن هذه الخوارزميات مرمزة
a sense of the public life, a sense of civic responsibility.
بنوع من حس الحياة العامة، حس من المسؤولية المدنية.
We need you to make sure that they're transparent enough
نريد أن نتيقن أنها شفافة بما فيه الكفاية
that we can see what the rules are
لتسمح لنا برؤية ما القواعد
that determine what gets through our filters.
التي تحدد ما الذي يعبر المرشحات.
And we need you to give us some control
ونحتاج أن تعطونا بعض التحكم،
so that we can decide
حتى يمكننا تحديد
what gets through and what doesn't.
ما يعبر وما لا يعبر.
Because I think
لأنه أعتقد
we really need the Internet to be that thing
أننا نحتاج بالفعل من الانترنت أن تكون ذلك الشيء
that we all dreamed of it being.
الذي حلمنا به.
We need it to connect us all together.
نريد منها أن تربطنا جميعا.
We need it to introduce us to new ideas
نريد منها أن تطلعنا على أفكار جديدة
and new people and different perspectives.
وأناس جدد بوجهات نظر مختلفة.
And it's not going to do that
ولن تقوم بذلك
if it leaves us all isolated in a Web of one.
إن تركتنا منعزلين في شبكة انترنت فردية.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)